<topic id="PHP34623" outputclass="drugClass">
    <title>CORTICOSTEROIDS (SYSTEMIC)</title>
    <topic id="PHP37530" outputclass="contraindications">
     <title>Contra-indications</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="contraindications"><p><ph outputclass="contraindication">Avoid live
         virus vaccines in those receiving immunosuppressive doses (serum antibody response
         diminished)</ph>; <ph outputclass="contraindication">systemic infection (unless specific
         therapy given)</ph></p>
      </section>
      <section outputclass="importantAdvice"><title>Contra-indications, further
         information</title><sectiondiv><p outputclass="specificity">With <ph outputclass="route"
          >intra-articular</ph> use or <ph outputclass="route">intradermal</ph> use or <ph
          outputclass="route">intralesional</ph> use</p><p>For further information on
         contraindications associated with intra-articular, intradermal and intralesional
         preparations, consult product literature.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37541" outputclass="cautions">
     <title>Cautions</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="cautions"><p><ph outputclass="caution">Congestive heart failure</ph>;
         <ph outputclass="caution">diabetes mellitus (including a family history of)</ph>; <ph
         outputclass="caution">diverticulitis</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">epilepsy</ph>; <ph
         outputclass="caution">glaucoma (including a family history of or susceptibility to)</ph>;
         <ph outputclass="caution">history of steroid myopathy</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution"
         >history of tuberculosis or X-ray changes (frequent monitoring required)</ph>; <ph
         outputclass="caution">hypertension</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">hypothyroidism</ph>; <ph
         outputclass="caution">infection (particularly untreated)</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution"
         >myasthenia gravis</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">ocular herpes simplex (risk of corneal
         perforation)</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">osteoporosis (post-menopausal women and the
         elderly at special risk)</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">peptic ulcer</ph>; <ph
         outputclass="caution">psychiatric reactions</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">recent
         intestinal anastomoses</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">recent myocardial infarction
         (rupture reported)</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">severe affective disorders (particularly
         if history of steroid-induced psychosis)</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">should not be used
         long-term</ph>; <ph outputclass="caution">thromboembolic disorders</ph>; <ph
         outputclass="caution">ulcerative colitis</ph></p>
      </section>
      <section outputclass="importantAdvice"><title>Cautions, further
         information</title><sectiondiv><p outputclass="specificity">With <ph outputclass="route"
          >intra-articular</ph> use or <ph outputclass="route">intradermal</ph> use or <ph
          outputclass="route">intralesional</ph> use</p><p>For further information on cautions
         associated with intra-articular, intradermal and intralesional preparations, consult
         product literature.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37497" outputclass="interactions">
     <title>Interactions</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="general"><sectiondiv><p>Appendix 1 (corticosteroids).</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37469" outputclass="sideEffects">
     <title>Side-effects</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="frequencies">
       <sectiondiv outputclass="notKnown">
        <p outputclass="title">Frequency not known</p>
        <sectiondiv outputclass="sideEffects">
         <p outputclass="title">General side-effects:</p>
         <p>
          <ph outputclass="sideEffect">Abdominal distension</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">acute
           pancreatitis</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">aggravation of epilepsy</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">aggravation of schizophrenia</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >amenorrhoea</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">bruising</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">candidiasis</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">congestive heart
           failure</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">corneal thinning</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">Cushing's syndrome (with moon face, striae and acne)</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">dyspepsia</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">ecchymoses</ph>;
           <ph outputclass="sideEffect">exacerbation of ophthalmic fungal disease</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">exacerbation of ophthalmic viral disease</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">exophthalmos</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">facial
           erythema</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">glaucoma</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >headache</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">hiccups</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >hirsutism</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">hypercholesterolaemia</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">hyperglycaemia</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >hyperhidrosis</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">hyperlipidaemia</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">impaired healing</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">increased
           appetite</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">increased intra-ocular pressure</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">increased susceptibility to and severity of infection</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">insomnia</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">leucocytosis</ph>;
           <ph outputclass="sideEffect">long bone fractures</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >malaise</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">menstrual irregularities</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">muscle weakness</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">myocardial
           rupture following recent myocardial infarction</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >nausea</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">negative calcium balance</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">negative nitrogen balance</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >oesophageal ulceration</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">papilloedema</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">petechiae</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">posterior
           subcapsular cataracts</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">potassium loss</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">psychological dependence</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >reactivation of dormant tuberculosis</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">scleral
           thinning</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">skin atrophy</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">sodium retention</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >telangiectasia</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">tendon rupture</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">thromboembolism</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect"
           >urticaria</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">vertebral fractures</ph>; <ph
           outputclass="sideEffect">vertigo</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">water retention</ph>;
           <ph outputclass="sideEffect">weight gain</ph>
         </p>
         <sectiondiv outputclass="additionalSideEffects">
          <p outputclass="title">Specific side-effects:</p>
          <sectiondiv outputclass="sideEffectsWithRoutes">
           <p outputclass="title">With intra-articular use</p>
           <p>
            <ph outputclass="sideEffect">flushing</ph>; <ph outputclass="sideEffect">may affect the
             hyaline cartilage</ph>
           </p>
          </sectiondiv>
         </sectiondiv>
        </sectiondiv>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
      <section outputclass="sideEffectsAdvice">
       <title>Side-effects, further information</title>
       <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="specificity">With <ph outputclass="route">intra-articular</ph> use or <ph
          outputclass="route">intradermal</ph> use or <ph outputclass="route">intralesional</ph>
         use</p>
        <p>For further information on side-effects associated with intra-articular, intradermal and
         intralesional preparations, consult product literature.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
       <sectiondiv>
        <p>Side effects can be managed by choice of route and duration of course. For further detail
         see <xref format="dita" href="#PHP78293" type="bookmark">Corticosteroids, general
          use</xref>
        </p>
       </sectiondiv>
       <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Adrenal suppression</p>
        <p>During prolonged therapy with corticosteroids, particularly with systemic use, adrenal
         atrophy develops and can persist for years after stopping. Abrupt withdrawal after a
         prolonged period can lead to acute adrenal insufficiency, hypotension, or death.</p>
        <p>To compensate for a diminished adrenocortical response caused by prolonged corticosteroid
         treatment, any significant intercurrent illness, trauma, or surgical procedure requires a
         temporary increase in corticosteroid dose, or if already stopped, a temporary
         reintroduction of corticosteroid treatment. To avoid a precipitous fall in blood pressure
         during anaesthesia or in the immediate postoperative period, anaesthetists <b>must</b> know
         whether a patient is taking or has been taking a corticosteroid. A suitable regimen for
         corticosteroid replacement, in patients who have taken more than 10 mg prednisolone daily
         (or equivalent) within 3 months of surgery, is:</p>
        <ul>
         <li>Minor surgery under general anaesthesia—usual oral corticosteroid dose on the morning
          of surgery or hydrocortisone (usually the sodium succinate) intravenously at induction;
          the usual oral corticosteroid dose is recommenced after surgery.</li>
         <li>Moderate or major surgery—usual oral corticosteroid dose on the morning of surgery and
          hydrocortisone intravenously at induction, followed by hydrocortisone 3 times a day by
          intravenous injection for 24 hours after moderate surgery or for 48–72 hours after major
          surgery; the usual pre-operative oral corticosteroid dose is recommenced on stopping
          hydrocortisone injections.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Patients on long-term corticosteroid treatment should carry a steroid treatment card
         which gives guidance on minimising risk and provides details of prescriber, drug, dosage
         and duration of treatment.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
       <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Infections</p>
        <p>Prolonged courses of corticosteroids increase susceptibility to infections and severity
         of infections; clinical presentation of infections may also be atypical. Serious infections
         e.g. <i>septicaemia</i> and <i>tuberculosis</i> may reach an advanced stage before being
         recognised, and <i>amoebiasis</i> or <i>strongyloidiasis</i> may be activated or
         exacerbated (exclude before initiating a corticosteroid in those at risk or with suggestive
         symptoms). Fungal or viral <i>ocular infections</i> may also be exacerbated.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
         <p outputclass="title">Chickenpox</p>
         <p>Unless they have had chickenpox, patients receiving oral or parenteral corticosteroids
          for purposes other than replacement should be regarded as being <i>at risk of severe
           chickenpox</i> (see Steroid Treatment Card). Manifestations of fulminant illness include
          pneumonia, hepatitis and disseminated intravascular coagulation; rash is not necessarily a
          prominent feature.</p>
         <p>Passive immunisation with varicella–zoster immunoglobulin is needed for exposed
          non–immune patients receiving systemic corticosteroids or for those who have used them
          within the previous 3 months. Confirmed chickenpox warrants specialist care and urgent
          treatment. Corticosteroids should not be stopped and dosage may need to be increased.</p>
         <p>Topical, inhaled or rectal corticosteroids are less likely to be associated with an
          increased risk of severe chickenpox.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
         <p outputclass="title">Measles</p>
         <p>Patients taking corticosteroids should be advised to take particular care to avoid
          exposure to measles and to seek immediate medical advice if exposure occurs. Prophylaxis
          with intramuscular normal immunoglobulin may be needed.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
       </sectiondiv>
       <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Psychiatric reactions</p>
        <p>Systemic corticosteroids, particularly in high doses, are linked to psychiatric reactions
         including euphoria, nightmares, insomnia, irritability, mood lability, suicidal thoughts,
         psychotic reactions, and behavioural disturbances. A serious paranoid state or depression
         with risk of suicide can be induced, particularly in patients with a history of mental
         disorder. These reactions frequently subside on reducing the dose or discontinuing the
         corticosteroid but they may also require specific management. Patients should be advised to
         seek medical advice if psychiatric symptoms (especially depression and suicidal thoughts)
         occur and they should also be alert to the rare possibility of such reactions during
         withdrawal of corticosteroid treatment.</p>
        <p>Systemic corticosteroids should be prescribed with care in those predisposed to
         psychiatric reactions, including those who have previously suffered corticosteroid–induced
         psychosis, or who have a personal or family history of psychiatric disorders.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37491" outputclass="pregnancy">
     <title>Pregnancy</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="generalInformation"><sectiondiv><p>The benefit of treatment with
         corticosteroids during pregnancy outweighs the risk. Corticosteroid cover is required
         during labour.</p><p>Following a review of the data on the safety of systemic
         corticosteroids used in pregnancy and breast-feeding the CSM (May 1998) concluded that
         corticosteroids vary in their ability to cross the placenta but there is no convincing
         evidence that systemic corticosteroids increase the incidence of congenital abnormalities
         such as cleft palate or lip. When administration is prolonged or repeated during pregnancy,
         systemic corticosteroids increase the risk of intra-uterine growth restriction; there is no
         evidence of intra-uterine growth restriction following short-term treatment (e.g.
         prophylactic treatment for neonatal respiratory distress syndrome). Any adrenal suppression
         in the neonate following prenatal exposure usually resolves spontaneously after birth and
         is rarely clinically important.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
      <section outputclass="additionalMonitoringInPregnancy"><sectiondiv><p>Pregnant women with
         fluid retention should be monitored closely when given systemic corticosteroids.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37553" outputclass="breastFeeding">
     <title>Breast feeding</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="generalInformation"><sectiondiv><p>The benefit of treatment with
         corticosteroids during breast-feeding outweighs the risk.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37507" outputclass="hepaticImpairment">
     <title>Hepatic impairment</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="generalInformation"><sectiondiv><p>The plasma-drug concentration may be
         increased (particularly on systemic use). Oral and parenteral use should be undertaken with
         caution.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37483" outputclass="renalImpairment">
     <title>Renal impairment</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="generalInformation"><sectiondiv><p>Use by oral and injectable routes
         should be undertaken with caution.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37450" outputclass="effectOnLaboratoryTests">
     <title>Effect on laboratory tests</title>
     <body>
      <section><sectiondiv><p outputclass="specificity">With <ph outputclass="route"
          >intramuscular</ph> use or <ph outputclass="route">intravenous</ph> use or <ph
          outputclass="route">oral</ph> use or <ph outputclass="route">rectal</ph>
         use</p><p>Suppression of skin test reactions.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37461" outputclass="treatmentCessation">
     <title>Treatment cessation</title>
     <body>
      <section><sectiondiv><p>Abrupt withdrawal after a prolonged period can lead to acute adrenal
         insufficiency, hypotension or death. Withdrawal can also be associated with fever, myalgia,
         arthralgia, rhinitis, conjunctivitis, painful itchy skin nodules and weight loss.</p><p>The
         magnitude and speed of dose reduction in corticosteroid withdrawal should be determined on
         a case-by–case basis, taking into consideration the underlying condition that is being
         treated, and individual patient factors such as the likelihood of relapse and the duration
         of corticosteroid treatment. <i>Gradual</i> withdrawal of systemic corticosteroids should
         be considered in those whose disease is unlikely to relapse and have:</p><ul>
         <li>received more than 40 mg prednisolone (or equivalent) daily for more than 1 week;</li>
         <li>been given repeat doses in the evening;</li>
         <li>received more than 3 weeks’ treatment;</li>
         <li>recently received repeated courses (particularly if taken for longer than 3
          weeks);</li>
         <li>taken a short course within 1 year of stopping long-term therapy;</li>
         <li>other possible causes of adrenal suppression.</li>
        </ul><p>Systemic corticosteroids may be stopped abruptly in those whose disease is unlikely
         to relapse <i>and</i> who have received treatment for 3 weeks or less <i>and</i> who are
         not included in the patient groups described above.</p><p>During corticosteroid withdrawal
         the dose may be reduced rapidly down to physiological doses (equivalent to prednisolone
         7.5 mg daily) and then reduced more slowly. Assessment of the disease may be needed during
         withdrawal to ensure that relapse does not occur.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="PHP37486" outputclass="patientAndCarerAdvice">
     <title>Patient and carer advice</title>
     <body>
      <section outputclass="patientResources">
       <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Advice for patients</p>
        <p>Patients on long-term corticosteroid treatment should carry a Steroid Treatment Card
         which gives guidance on minimising risk and provides details of prescriber, drug, dosage
         and duration of treatment.</p>
        <p>A patient information leaflet should be supplied to every patient when a systemic
         corticosteroid is prescribed. Patients should especially be advised of the following:</p>
        <ul>
         <li>
          <b>Immunosuppression</b> Prolonged courses of corticosteroids can increase susceptibility
          to infection and serious infections can go unrecognised. Unless already immune, patients
          are at risk of severe <b>chickenpox</b> and should avoid close contact with people who
          have chickenpox or shingles. Similarly, precautions should also be taken against
          contracting <b>measles</b>;</li>
         <li>
          <b>Adrenal suppression</b> If the corticosteroid is given for longer than 3 weeks,
          treatment must not be stopped abruptly. Adrenal suppression can last for a year or more
          after stopping treatment and the patient must mention the course of corticosteroid when
          receiving treatment for any illness or injury;</li>
         <li>
          <b>Mood and behaviour changes</b> Corticosteroid treatment, especially with high doses,
          can alter mood and behaviour early in treatment—the patient can become confused, irritable
          and suffer from delusion and suicidal thoughts. These effects can also occur when
          corticosteroid treatment is being withdrawn. Medical advice should be sought if worrying
          psychological changes occur;</li>
         <li>
          <b>Other serious effects</b> Serious gastro-intestinal, musculoskeletal, and ophthalmic
          effects which require medical help can also occur.</li>
        </ul>
       </sectiondiv>
       <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Steroid treatment cards</p>
        <p>Steroid treatment cards should be issued where appropriate. Consider giving a ‘steroid
         card’ to support communication of the risks associated with treatment, and specific written
         advice to consider corticosteroid replacement during an episode of stress, such as severe
         intercurrent illness or an operation, to patients using greater than maximum licensed doses
         of inhaled corticosteroids. Steroid treatment cards are available for purchase from:</p>
        <sectiondiv outputclass="organization">
         <p outputclass="title">3M Security Print and Systems LimitedGorse StreetChaddertonOldhamOL9
          9QH</p>
         <ul>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">Gorse Street</li>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">Chadderton</li>
          <li outputclass="address">Oldham OL9 9QH</li>
          <li outputclass="contactnumber">Tel: 0845 610 1112</li>
         </ul>
        </sectiondiv>
        <p>GP practices can obtain supplies through their Local Area Team Stores. NHS Trusts can
         order supplies from <xref format="html" href="https://www.nhsforms.co.uk"
          >www.nhsforms.co.uk</xref>or by emailing nhsforms@mmm.com.</p>
        <p>In <b>Scotland</b>, steroid treatment cards can be obtained from APS Group Scotland by
         emailing stockorders.dppas@theapsgroup.com or by fax on 0131 629 9967.</p>
       </sectiondiv>
      </section>
     </body>
    </topic>
   </topic>
