<topic id="PHP78335" outputclass="treatmentSummary comparativeInformation" rev="1.298">
  <title>Vaccines</title>
  <body>
    <data name="doi">doi:10.18578/BNF_860949239</data>
    <data name="bodySystem">vaccines</data>
    <section>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Active immunity</p>
        <p>Active immunity can be acquired by natural disease or by vaccination. <b>Vaccines</b> stimulate production of antibodies and other components of the immune mechanism; they consist of either:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>a <i>live attenuated</i> form of a virus (e.g. measles, mumps and rubella vaccine) or bacteria (e.g. BCG vaccine), or</li>
          <li>
            <i>inactivated</i> preparations of the virus (e.g. influenza vaccine) or bacteria, or</li>
          <li>
            <i>detoxified exotoxins</i> produced by a micro-organism (e.g. tetanus vaccine), or</li>
          <li>
            <i>extracts of</i> a micro-organism, which may be derived from the organism (e.g. pneumococcal vaccine) or produced by recombinant DNA technology (e.g. hepatitis B vaccine).</li>
        </ol>
        <p>
          <b>Live attenuated</b>
          <b>vaccines</b> usually produce a durable immunity, but not always as long-lasting as that resulting from natural infection.</p>
        <p>
          <b>Inactivated vaccines</b> may require a primary series of injections of vaccine to produce an adequate antibody response, and in most cases booster (reinforcing) injections are required; the duration of immunity varies from months to many years. Some inactivated vaccines are adsorbed onto an adjuvant (such as aluminium hydroxide) to enhance the antibody response.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p>Advice reflects that in the handbook <i>Immunisation against Infectious Disease</i> (2006), which in turn reflects the guidance of the Joint Committee on Vaccination and Immunisation (JCVI).</p>
          <p>Chapters from the handbook are available at <xref format="html" href="http://www.immunisation.dh.gov.uk">www.immunisation.dh.gov.uk</xref></p>
          <p>The advice also incorporates changes announced by the Chief Medical Officer and Health Department Updates.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section outputclass="adult">
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Active immunity</p>
        <p>Active immunity can be acquired by natural disease or by vaccination. <b>Vaccines</b> stimulate production of antibodies and other components of the immune mechanism; they consist of either:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>a <i>live attenuated</i> form of a virus (e.g. measles, mumps and rubella vaccine) or bacteria (e.g. BCG vaccine), or</li>
          <li>
            <i>inactivated</i> preparations of the virus (e.g. influenza vaccine) or bacteria, or</li>
          <li>
            <i>detoxified exotoxins</i> produced by a micro-organism (e.g. tetanus vaccine), or</li>
          <li>
            <i>extracts of</i> a micro-organism, which may be derived from the organism (e.g. pneumococcal vaccine) or produced by recombinant DNA technology (e.g. hepatitis B vaccine).</li>
        </ol>
        <p>
          <b>Live attenuated</b>
          <b>vaccines</b> usually produce a durable immunity, but not always as long-lasting as that resulting from natural infection.</p>
        <p>
          <b>Inactivated vaccines</b> may require a primary series of injections of vaccine to produce an adequate antibody response, and in most cases booster (reinforcing) injections are required; the duration of immunity varies from months to many years. Some inactivated vaccines are adsorbed onto an adjuvant (such as aluminium hydroxide) to enhance the antibody response.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p>Advice reflects that in the handbook <i>Immunisation against Infectious Disease</i> (2006), which in turn reflects the guidance of the Joint Committee on Vaccination and Immunisation (JCVI).</p>
          <p>Chapters from the handbook are available at <xref format="html" href="http://www.immunisation.dh.gov.uk">www.immunisation.dh.gov.uk</xref></p>
          <p>The advice also incorporates changes announced by the Chief Medical Officer and Health Department Updates.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Immunisation schedule</p>
        <p>Vaccines for the childhood immunisation schedule should be obtained from <b>local health organisations</b> or <b>from ImmForm</b> (<xref format="html" href="https://www.immform.dh.gov.uk">www.immform.dh.gov.uk</xref>)—not to be prescribed on FP10 (HS21 in Northern Ireland; GP10 in Scotland; WP10 in Wales).</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Preterm birth</p>
          <p>Babies born preterm should receive all routine immunisations based on their actual date of birth. The risk of apnoea following vaccination is increased in preterm babies, particularly in those born at or before 28 weeks gestational age. If babies at risk of apnoea are in hospital at the time of their first immunisation, they should be monitored for 48 hours after immunisation. If a baby develops apnoea, bradycardia, or desaturation after the first immunisation, the second immunisation should also be given in hospital with similar monitoring. Seroconversion may be unreliable in babies born earlier than 28 weeks’ gestation or in babies treated with corticosteroids for chronic lung disease; consideration should be given to testing for antibodies against <i>Haemophilus influenzae</i> type b, meningococcal C, and hepatitis B after primary immunisation.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <fig>
          <title />
          <simpletable>
            <sthead>
              <stentry>When to immunise</stentry>
              <stentry>Vaccine given and dose schedule (for details of dose, see under individual vaccines)</stentry>
            </sthead>
            <strow>
              <stentry>Neonates at risk only</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8249.xml" type="drug">bacillus calmette-guérin vaccine</xref>
              </stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8310.xml" type="drug">hepatitis B vaccine</xref>
              </stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>2 months</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88117.xml" type="drug">diphtheria with haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine, pertussis, poliomyelitis and tetanus </xref> First dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8373.xml" type="drug">pneumococcal vaccine</xref> First dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8396.xml" type="drug">rotavirus vaccine</xref> First dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>3 months</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88117.xml" type="drug">diphtheria with haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine, pertussis, poliomyelitis and tetanus </xref> Second dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP99985.xml" type="drug">meningococcal group C vaccine</xref> First dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8396.xml" type="drug">rotavirus vaccine</xref> Second dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>4 months</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88117.xml" type="drug">diphtheria with haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine, pertussis, poliomyelitis and tetanus </xref> Third dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8373.xml" type="drug">pneumococcal vaccine</xref> Second dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>12–13 months</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> First dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8373.xml" type="drug">pneumococcal vaccine</xref> Single booster dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88120.xml" type="drug">haemophilus influenzae type B with meningococcal group C vaccine</xref> Single booster dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>Between 3 years and 4 months, and 5 years</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88118.xml" type="drug">diphtheria with pertussis, poliomyelitis vaccine and tetanus </xref> Single booster dose. <b>Note</b>: Preferably allow interval of at least 3 years after completing primary course</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> Second dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>11–14 years (females only). First dose of HPV vaccine will be offered to females aged 12–13 years of age in England, Wales, and Northern Ireland, and 11–14 years of age in Scotland.</stentry>
              <stentry>Human papillomavirus vaccines If a 3-dose course of HPV vaccine has been started under the 2013/2014 programme, where possible, the course should be completed. The two human papillomavirus vaccines are not interchangeable and, ideally, one vaccine product should be used for the entire course. However, for those females who started the schedule with <i>Cervarix</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> under the national immunisation programme, but did not complete the vaccination course, the course can be completed with <i>Gardasil</i><tm tmtype="reg" />.</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>13–15 years</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP99985.xml" type="drug">meningococcal group C vaccine</xref> Single booster dose</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>13–18 years</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88119.xml" type="drug">diphtheria with poliomyelitis and tetanus vaccine</xref> Single booster dose. <b>Note:</b> Can be given at the same time as the booster dose of meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine at 13–15 years of age.</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>During adult life, women of child-bearing age susceptible to rubella</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> Women of child-bearing age who have not received 2 doses of a rubella-containing vaccine or who do not have a positive antibody test for rubella should be offered rubella immunisation (using the MMR vaccine)—exclude pregnancy before immunisation.</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>During adult life, those entering or being at university who are at risk of meningococcal group C disease</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP99985.xml" type="drug">meningococcal group C vaccine</xref> Single dose. <b>Note:</b> Should be offered to those of any age entering or being at university who have never been vaccinated against meningococcal group C disease, or those born after September 1995 who are entering university and only received meningococcal group C vaccine under the age of 10 years</stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>During adult life, if not previously immunised</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP88119.xml" type="drug">diphtheria with poliomyelitis and tetanus vaccine</xref>
              </stentry>
            </strow>
            <strow>
              <stentry>70 years</stentry>
              <stentry>
                <xref format="dita" href="PHP8420.xml" type="drug">varicella-zoster vaccine</xref> Single dose</stentry>
            </strow>
          </simpletable>
        </fig>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Vaccines and HIV infection</p>
          <p>HIV-positive individuals with or without symptoms can receive the following live vaccines:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>MMR (but avoid if immunity significantly impaired; use of normal immunoglobulin should be considered after exposure to measles), varicella-zoster vaccine against chickenpox (but avoid if immunity significantly impaired—consult product literature; varicella–zoster immunoglobulin should be considered after exposure to chickenpox or herpes zoster), rotavirus;</li>
          </ul>
          <p>and the following inactivated vaccines:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>anthrax, cholera (oral), diphtheria, haemophilus influenzae type b, hepatitis A, hepatitis B, human papillomavirus, influenza (injection), meningococcal, pertussis, pneumococcal, poliomyelitis, rabies, tetanus, tick-borne encephalitis, typhoid (injection).</li>
          </ul>
          <p>HIV-positive individuals should <b>not</b> receive:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>BCG, influenza nasal spray (unless stable HIV infection and receiving antiretroviral therapy), typhoid (oral), yellow fever (if yellow fever risk is unavoidable, specialist advice should be sought)</li>
          </ul>
          <p>The above advice differs from that for other immunocompromised patients; <i>Immunisation Guidelines for HIV-infected Adults</i> issued by <i>British HIV Association</i> (BHIVA) are available at <xref format="html" href="http://www.bhiva.org">www.bhiva.org</xref></p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Vaccines and asplenia</p>
          <p>The following vaccines are recommended for asplenic patients or those with splenic dysfunction: </p>
          <ul>
            <li>haemophilus influenzae type b; influenza; meningococcal A, C, W135, and Y conjugate; pneumococcal.</li>
          </ul>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Vaccines and antisera availability</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8245.xml" type="drug">Anthrax vaccine</xref> and <xref format="dita" href="PHP8427.xml" type="drug">yellow fever vaccine, live</xref>, <xref format="dita" href="PHP34501.xml" type="drug">botulism antitoxin</xref>, <xref format="dita" href="PHP93586.xml" type="drug">diphtheria antitoxin</xref>, and snake and spider venom antitoxins are available from local designated holding centres.</p>
        <p>For antivenom, see <xref format="dita" href="PHP78558.xml" type="bookmark">Emergency treatment of poisoning</xref>.</p>
        <p>Enquiries for vaccines not available commercially can also be made to:</p>
        <ul outputclass="organization">
          <li outputclass="namedetailsdepartmentname">Vaccines and Countermeasures Response Department</li>
          <li outputclass="organizationname">Public Health England</li>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">Wellington House</li>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">133–155 Waterloo Road</li>
          <li outputclass="localityname">London</li>
          <li outputclass="postalcode">SE1 8UG</li>
          <li outputclass="emailaddress">vaccinesupply@phe.gov.uk</li>
        </ul>
        <p>In Scotland information about availability of vaccines can be obtained from a Specialist in Pharmaceutical Public Health.</p>
        <p>In Wales enquiries for vaccines not available commercially should be directed to:</p>
        <ul outputclass="organization">
          <li outputclass="namedetailsdepartmentname">Welsh Medicines Information Centre</li>
          <li outputclass="organizationname">University Hospital of Wales</li>
          <li outputclass="localityname">Cardiff</li>
          <li outputclass="postalcode">CF14 4XW</li>
          <li outputclass="contactnumber">(029) 2074 2979</li>
        </ul>
        <p>In Northern Ireland:</p>
        <ul outputclass="organization">
          <li outputclass="namedetailsdepartmentname">Pharmacy and Medicines Management Centre</li>
          <li outputclass="organizationname">Northern Health and Social Care Trust</li>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">Beech House</li>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">Antrim Hospital Site</li>
          <li outputclass="thoroughfare">Bush Road</li>
          <li outputclass="localityname">Antrim</li>
          <li outputclass="postalcode">BT41 2RL</li>
          <li outputclass="emailaddress">rphps.admin@northerntrust.hscni.net</li>
        </ul>
        <p>For further details of availability, see under individual vaccines.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Anthrax vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8245.xml" type="drug">Anthrax vaccine</xref> is made from antigens from <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>B. anthracis</i></i></ph>. Anthrax immunisation is indicated for individuals who handle infected animals, for those exposed to imported infected animal products, and for laboratory staff who work with <i>B. anthracis</i>. A 4-dose regimen is used for primary immunisation; booster doses should be given annually to workers at continued risk of exposure to anthrax.</p>
        <p>In the event of possible contact with <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>B. anthracis</i></i></ph>, post-exposure immunisation may be indicated, in addition to antimicrobial prophylaxis. Advice on the use of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8245.xml" type="drug">anthrax vaccine</xref> for post-exposure prophylaxis must be obtained from Public Health England Colindale (tel. 020 8200 4400).</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">BCG vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8249.xml" type="drug">Bacillus calmette-guérin vaccine</xref> should be given intradermally by operators skilled in the technique.</p>
        <p>The expected reaction to successful <xref format="dita" href="PHP8249.xml" type="drug">bacillus calmette-guérin vaccine</xref> is induration at the site of injection followed by a local lesion which starts as a papule 2 or more weeks after vaccination; the lesion may ulcerate then subside over several weeks or months, leaving a small, flat scar. A dry dressing may be used if the ulcer discharges, but air should <b>not</b> be excluded.</p>
        <p>BCG is recommended for the following groups if BCG immunisation has not previously been carried out and they are negative for tuberculoprotein hypersensitivity:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>neonates with a family history of tuberculosis in the last 5 years;</li>
          <li>all neonates and infants (0–12 months) born in areas where the incidence of tuberculosis is greater than 40 per 100 000;</li>
          <li>neonates, infants, and children under 16 years with a parent or grandparent born in a country with an incidence of tuberculosis greater than 40 per 100 000;</li>
          <li>new immigrants aged under 16 years who were born in, or lived for more than 3 months in a country with an incidence of tuberculosis greater than 40 per 100 000;</li>
          <li>new immigrants aged 16–35 years from Sub-Saharan Africa or a country with an incidence of tuberculosis greater than 500 per 100 000;</li>
          <li>contacts aged under 36 years of those with active respiratory tuberculosis (for healthcare or laboratory workers who have had contact with clinical materials or patients with tuberculosis, age limit does not apply);</li>
          <li>healthcare workers and laboratory staff (irrespective of age) who are likely to have contact with patients, clinical materials, or derived isolates; other individuals under 35 years (there is inadequate evidence of protection by BCG vaccine in adults aged over 35 years; however, vaccination is recommended for healthcare workers irrespective of age because of the increased risk to them or their patients) at occupational risk including veterinary and other staff who handle animal species susceptible to tuberculosis, and staff working directly with prisoners, in care homes for the elderly, or in hostels or facilities for the homeless or refugees;</li>
          <li>individuals under 16 years intending to live with local people for more than 3 months in a country with an incidence of tuberculosis greater than 40 per 100 000.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>List of countries or primary care trusts where the incidence of tuberculosis is greater than 40 cases per 100 000 is available at <xref format="html" href="http://www.gov.uk/phe">www.gov.uk/phe</xref>.</p>
        <p>Bladder instillations of BCG are licensed for the management of bladder carcinoma.</p>
        <p>See also <xref format="dita" href="PHP78330.xml" type="bookmark">Tuberculosis</xref> for advice on chemoprophylaxis; for the treatment of infection following vaccination, seek expert advice.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Tuberculosis Diagnostic Agents</p>
        <p>The <i>Mantoux test</i> is recommended for tuberculin skin testing, but no licensed preparation is currently available. Guidance for healthcare professionals is available at <xref format="html" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/immunisation">www.dh.gov.uk/immunisation</xref>.</p>
        <p>In the Mantoux test, the diagnostic dose is administered by intradermal injection of <xref format="dita" href="PHP34509.xml" type="drug">tuberculin purified protein derivative</xref> (PPD).</p>
        <p>The <i>Heaf test</i> (involving the use of multiple-puncture apparatus) is no longer available.</p>
        <p>Two interferon gamma release assay (IGRA) tests are also available as an aid in the diagnosis of tuberculosis infection: <i>QuanitFERON</i><tm tmtype="reg" /><i>TB Gold</i> and <i>T-SPOT</i><tm tmtype="reg" />.TB. Both tests measure T-cell mediated immune response to synthetic antigens. For further information on the use of interferon gamma release assay tests for tuberculosis, see <xref format="html" href="http://www.gov.uk/phe">www.gov.uk/phe</xref>.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Botulism antitoxin</p>
        <p>A polyvalent <xref format="dita" href="PHP34501.xml" type="drug">botulism antitoxin</xref> is available for the post-exposure prophylaxis of botulism and for the treatment of persons thought to be suffering from botulism. It specifically neutralises the toxins produced by <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Clostridium botulinum</i></i></ph> types A, B, and E. It is not effective against infantile botulism as the toxin (type A) is seldom, if ever, found in the blood in this type of infection.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Cholera vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8260.xml" type="drug">Cholera vaccine</xref> (oral) contains inactivated Inaba (including El-Tor biotype) and Ogawa strains of <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Vibrio cholerae</i></i></ph>, serotype O1 together with recombinant B-subunit of the cholera toxin produced in Inaba strains of <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>V.cholerae</i></i></ph>, serotype O1.</p>
        <p>Oral <xref format="dita" href="PHP8260.xml" type="drug">cholera vaccine</xref> is licensed for travellers to endemic or epidemic areas on the basis of current recommendations. Immunisation should be completed at least 1 week before potential exposure. However, there is no requirement for cholera vaccination for international travel.</p>
        <p>
          <i>Injectable cholera vaccine </i>provides unreliable protection and is no longer available in the UK.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Diphtheria vaccine</p>
        <p>Diphtheria-containing vaccines are prepared from the toxin of <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Corynebacterium diphtheriae</i></i></ph> and adsorption on aluminium hydroxide or aluminium phosphate improves antigenicity. The vaccine stimulates the production of the protective antibody. The quantity of diphtheria toxoid in a preparation determines whether the vaccine is defined as ‘high dose’ or ‘low dose’. Vaccines containing the higher dose of diphtheria toxoid are used for primary immunisation of children under 10 years of age. Vaccines containing the lower dose of diphtheria toxoid are used for primary immunisation in adults and children over 10 years. Single-antigen diphtheria vaccine is not available and adsorbed diphtheria vaccine is given as a combination product containing other vaccines.</p>
        <p>For primary immunisation <i>of children aged between 2 months and 10 years</i> vaccination is recommended usually in the form of 3 doses (separated by 1-month intervals) of <b>diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component), poliomyelitis (inactivated) and haemophilus type b conjugate vaccine (adsorbed)</b> (see Immunisation schedule). In unimmunised individuals aged <i>over 10 years</i> the primary course comprises of 3 doses of <b>adsorbed diphtheria</b> [low dose], <b>tetanus and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b>.</p>
        <p>A booster dose should be given 3 years after the primary course (this interval can be reduced to a minimum of 1 year if the primary course was delayed). Children <i>under 10 years</i> should receive <i>either</i><b>adsorbed diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component) and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b><i>or</i><b>adsorbed diphtheria</b> [low dose], <b>tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component) and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b>. Individuals aged <i>over 10 years</i> should receive <b>adsorbed diphtheria</b> [low dose], <b>tetanus, and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b>.</p>
        <p>A second booster dose, of adsorbed diphtheria [low dose], tetanus and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine, should be given 10 years after the previous booster dose (this interval can be reduced to a minimum of 5 years if previous doses were delayed).</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Diphtheria-containing vaccines for children over 10 years and adults</p>
          <p>A <b>low dose</b> of diphtheria toxoid is sufficient to recall immunity in individuals previously immunised against diphtheria but whose immunity may have diminished with time; it is insufficient to cause serious reactions in an individual who is already immune. Preparations containing low dose diphtheria should be used for adults and children <i>over 10 years</i>, for both primary immunisation and booster doses.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Travel</p>
          <p>Those intending to travel to areas with a risk of diphtheria infection should be fully immunised according to the UK schedule. If more than 10 years have lapsed since completion of the UK schedule, a dose of <b>adsorbed diphtheria</b> [low dose], <b>tetanus and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b> should be administered.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Contacts</p>
          <p>Staff in contact with diphtheria patients or with potentially pathogenic clinical specimens or working directly with <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>C. diphtheriae</i></i></ph> or <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>C. ulcerans</i></i></ph> should receive a booster dose if fully immunised (with 5 doses of diphtheria-containing vaccine given at appropriate intervals); further doses should be given at 10-year intervals if risk persists. Individuals at risk who are not fully immunised should complete the primary course; a booster dose should be given after 5 years and then at 10-year intervals. <b>Adsorbed diphtheria</b> [low dose], <b>tetanus and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b> is used for this purpose; immunity should be checked by antibody testing at least 3 months after completion of immunisation.</p>
          <p>Advice on the management of cases, carriers, contacts and outbreaks must be sought from health protection units. The immunisation history of infected individuals and their contacts should be determined; those who have been incompletely immunised should complete their immunisation and fully immunised individuals should receive a reinforcing dose. See advice on antibacterial treatment to prevent a secondary case of diphtheria in a non-immune individual.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Haemophilus influenzae type B conjugate vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <b>Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) vaccine</b> is made from capsular polysaccharide; it is conjugated with a protein such as tetanus toxoid to increase immunogenicity, especially in young children. Haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine immunisation is given in combination with diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component) and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine, as a component of the primary course of childhood immunisation (see Immunisation schedule). For infants under 1 year, the course consists of 3 doses of a vaccine containing <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Haemophilus influenzae</i></i></ph> type b component with an interval of 1 month between doses. A booster dose of haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine) should be given at 12–13 months of age.</p>
        <p>Children 1–10 years who have not been immunised against <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Haemophilus influenzae</i></i></ph> type b need to receive only 1 dose of Haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine). However, if a primary course of immunisation has not been completed, these children should be given 3 doses of diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component), and poliomyelitis (inactivated). The risk of infection falls sharply in older children and the vaccine is not normally required for children over 10 years.</p>
        <p>Haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine may be given to those over 10 years who are considered to be at increased risk of invasive <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>H. influenzae</i></i></ph> type b disease (such as those with sickle-cell disease or complement deficiency, or those receiving treatment for malignancy).</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Invasive Haemophilus influenzae type b disease</p>
          <p>After recovery from infection, unimmunised and partially immunised index cases under 10 years of age should complete their age-specific course of immunisation. Previously vaccinated cases under 10 years of age should be given an additional dose of haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine) if Hib antibody concentrations are low or if it is not possible to measure antibody concentrations. Index cases of any age with asplenia or splenic dysfunction should complete their immunisation according to the recommendations below; fully vaccinated cases with asplenia or splenic dysfunction should be given an additional dose of haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine) if they received their previous dose over 1 year ago.</p>
          <p>See also use of <xref format="dita" href="PHP3619.xml" type="drug">rifampicin</xref> in the prevention of secondary cases of <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Haemophilus influenzae</i></i></ph> type b disease.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <p>Individuals diagnosed with asplenia, splenic dysfunction, or complement deficiency at:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <i>under 2 years of age</i> should be vaccinated according to the Immunisation Schedule. The booster dose of haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine), given at 12–13 months of age, should be followed at least 1 month later by one dose of meningococcal A, C, W135, and Y conjugate vaccine. An additional dose of haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine) should be given after the second birthday;</li>
          <li>
            <i>over 2 years of age</i> should receive one dose of haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine (combined with meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine), followed 1 month later by one dose of meningococcal A, C, W135, and Y conjugate vaccine.</li>
        </ul>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Hepatitis A vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8291.xml" type="drug">Hepatitis A vaccine</xref> is prepared from formaldehyde-inactivated hepatitis A virus grown in human diploid cells.</p>
        <p>Immunisation is recommended for:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>laboratory staff who work directly with the virus;</li>
          <li>staff and residents of homes for those with severe learning difficulties;</li>
          <li>workers at risk of exposure to untreated sewage;</li>
          <li>individuals who work with primates;</li>
          <li>patients with haemophilia or other conditions treated with plasma-derived clotting factors;</li>
          <li>patients with severe liver disease;</li>
          <li>travellers to high-risk areas;</li>
          <li>individuals who are at risk due to their sexual behaviour;</li>
          <li>parenteral drug abusers.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Immunisation should be considered for:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>patients with chronic liver disease including chronic hepatitis B or chronic hepatitis C;</li>
          <li>prevention of secondary cases in close contacts of confirmed cases of hepatitis A, within 14 days of exposure to the primary case (within 8 weeks of exposure to the primary case where there is more than 1 contact in the household).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>A booster dose is usually given 6–12 months after the initial dose. A second booster dose can be given 20 years after the previous booster dose to those who continue to be at risk. Specialist advice should be sought on re-immunisation of immunocompromised individuals.</p>
        <p>For rapid protection against hepatitis A after exposure or during an outbreak, in adults a single dose of a monovalent vaccine is recommended; for children under 16 years, a single dose of the combined vaccine Ambirix<tm tmtype="reg" /> can also be used.</p>
        <p>Intramuscular <xref format="dita" href="PHP8436.xml" type="drug">normal immunoglobulin</xref> is recommended for use in addition to <xref format="dita" href="PHP8291.xml" type="drug">hepatitis A vaccine</xref> for close contacts (of confirmed cases of hepatitis A) who have chronic liver disease or HIV infection, or who are immunosuppressed or over 50 years of age.</p>
        <p>Post-exposure prophylaxis is not required for healthy children under 1 year of age, so long as all those involved in nappy changing are vaccinated against hepatitis A. However, children 2–12 months of age can be given a dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8291.xml" type="drug">hepatitis A vaccine</xref> if it is not possible to vaccinate their carers, or if the child becomes a source of infection to others [unlicensed use]; in these cases, if the child goes on to require long-term protection against hepatitis A after the first birthday, the full course of 2 doses should be given.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Hepatitis B vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8310.xml" type="drug">Hepatitis B vaccine</xref> contains inactivated hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg) adsorbed onto aluminium hydroxide adjuvant. It is made biosynthetically using recombinant DNA technology. The vaccine is used in individuals at high risk of contracting hepatitis B.</p>
        <p>In the UK, groups at high-risk of hepatitis B include:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>parenteral drug misusers, their sexual partners, and household contacts; other drug misusers who are likely to ‘progress’ to injecting;</li>
          <li>individuals who change sexual partners frequently;</li>
          <li>close family contacts of a case or individual with chronic hepatitis B infection;</li>
          <li>babies whose mothers have had acute hepatitis B during pregnancy <i>or </i>are positive for hepatitis B surface antigen (regardless of e-antigen markers); hepatitis B vaccination is started immediately on delivery and <i>hepatitis B immunoglobulin</i> given at the same time (but preferably at a different site). Babies whose mothers are positive for hepatitis B surface antigen and for e-antigen antibody should receive the vaccine only (but babies weighing 1.5 kg or less should also receive the immunoglobulin regardless of the mother’s e-antigen antibody status);</li>
          <li>individuals with haemophilia, those receiving regular blood transfusions or blood products, and carers responsible for the administration of such products;</li>
          <li>patients with chronic renal failure including those on haemodialysis. Haemodialysis patients should be monitored for antibodies annually and re-immunised if necessary. Home carers (of dialysis patients) should be vaccinated;</li>
          <li>individuals with chronic liver disease;</li>
          <li>healthcare personnel (including trainees) who have direct contact with blood or blood-stained body fluids or with patients’ tissues;</li>
          <li>laboratory staff who handle material that may contain the virus;</li>
          <li>other occupational risk groups such as morticians and embalmers;</li>
          <li>staff and patients of day-care or residential accommodation for those with severe learning difficulties;</li>
          <li>staff and inmates of custodial institutions;</li>
          <li>those travelling to areas of high or intermediate prevalence who are at increased risk or who plan to remain there for lengthy periods;</li>
          <li>families adopting children from countries with a high or intermediate prevalence of hepatitis B;</li>
          <li>foster carers and their families.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Different immunisation schedules for <xref format="dita" href="PHP8310.xml" type="drug">hepatitis B vaccine</xref> are recommended for specific circumstances. Generally, three or four doses are required for primary immunisation; an ‘accelerated schedule’ is recommended for pre-exposure prophylaxis in high-risk groups where rapid protection is required, and for post-exposure prophylaxis.</p>
        <p>Immunisation may take up to 6 months to confer adequate protection; the duration of immunity is not known precisely, but a single booster 5 years after the primary course may be sufficient to maintain immunity for those who continue to be at risk.</p>
        <p>Immunisation does not eliminate the need for commonsense precautions for avoiding the risk of infection from known carriers by the routes of infection which have been clearly established, consult <i>Guidance for Clinical Health Care Workers: Protection against Infection with Blood-borne Viruses</i> (available at <xref format="html" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk">www.dh.gov.uk</xref>). Accidental inoculation of hepatitis B virus-infected blood into a wound, incision, needle-prick, or abrasion may lead to infection, whereas it is unlikely that indirect exposure to a carrier will do so.</p>
        <p>Following significant exposure to hepatitis B, an accelerated schedule, with the second dose given 1 month, and the third dose 2 months after the first dose, is recommended. For those at continued risk, a fourth dose should be given 12 months after the first dose. More detailed guidance is given in the handbook <i>Immunisation against Infectious Disease</i>. Specific <xref format="dita" href="PHP8462.xml" type="drug">hepatitis B immunoglobulin</xref> (‘HBIG’) is available for use with the vaccine in those accidentally inoculated and in neonates at special risk of infection.</p>
        <p>A combined <xref format="dita" href="PHP88121.xml" type="drug">hepatitis A and B vaccine</xref> is also available.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Human papillomavirus vaccine</p>
        <p>Human papillomavirus vaccine is available as a bivalent vaccine (<i>Cervarix</i><tm tmtype="reg" />) or a quadrivalent vaccine (<i>Gardasil </i><tm tmtype="reg" />). <i>Cervarix</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> is licensed for use in females for the prevention of cervical cancer and other pre-cancerous lesions caused by human papillomavirus types 16 and 18. <i>Gardasil </i><tm tmtype="reg" /> is licensed for use in females for the prevention of cervical and anal cancers, genital warts and pre-cancerous genital (cervical, vulvar, and vaginal) and anal lesions caused by human papillomavirus types 6, 11, 16, and 18. The vaccines may also provide limited protection against disease caused by other types of human papillomavirus. The two vaccines are not interchangeable and one vaccine product should be used for an entire course.</p>
        <p>Human papillomavirus vaccine will be most effective if given before sexual activity starts. From September 2014, a 2-dose schedule is recommended, as long as the first dose is received before the age of 15 years. The first dose is given to females aged 11 to 14 years, and the second dose is given 6–24 months after the first dose (for the purposes of planning the national immunisation programme, it is appropriate to give the second dose 12 months after the first (see Immunisation schedule). If the course is interrupted, it should be resumed (using the same vaccine) but not repeated, even if more than 24 months have elapsed since the first dose or if the girl is then aged 15 years or more. Females receiving their first dose aged 15 years or older require a 3-dose schedule (see <i>Cervarix</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> and <i>Gardasil</i><tm tmtype="reg" />), with the second and third doses given 1 and 4–6 months after the first dose; all 3 doses should be given within a 12-month period. If the course is interrupted, it should be resumed (using the same vaccine) but not repeated, allowing the appropriate interval between the remaining doses. If a 3-dose course of vaccination has been started before September 2014, then where possible this should be completed; if the course is interrupted, it should be resumed (using the same vaccine) but not repeated, allowing the appropriate interval between the remaining doses. Under the national programme in England, females remain eligible to receive the human papillomavirus vaccine up to the age of 18 years if they did not receive the vaccine when scheduled. Where appropriate, immunisation with human papillomavirus vaccine should be offered to females coming into the UK as they may not have been offered protection in their country of origin. The duration of protection has not been established, but current studies suggest that protection is maintained for at least 6 years after completion of the primary course.</p>
        <p>As the vaccines do not protect against all strains of human papillomavirus, routine cervical screening should continue.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Influenza vaccine</p>
        <p>While most viruses are antigenically stable, the influenza viruses A and B (especially A) are constantly altering their antigenic structure as indicated by changes in the haemagglutinins (H) and neuraminidases (N) on the surface of the viruses. It is essential that <xref format="dita" href="PHP8321.xml" type="drug">influenza vaccine</xref> in use contain the H and N components of the prevalent strain or strains as recommended each year by the World Health Organization.</p>
        <p>Immunisation is recommended <i>for persons at high risk</i>, and to reduce transmission of infection. Annual immunisation is strongly recommended for individuals aged over 6 months with the following conditions:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>chronic respiratory disease (includes asthma treated with continuous or repeated use of inhaled or systemic corticosteroids or asthma with previous exacerbations requiring hospital admission);</li>
          <li>chronic heart disease;</li>
          <li>chronic liver disease;</li>
          <li>chronic renal disease;</li>
          <li>chronic neurological disease;</li>
          <li>diabetes mellitus;</li>
          <li>immunosuppression because of disease (including asplenia or splenic dysfunction) or treatment (including prolonged systemic corticosteroid treatment [for over 1 month at dose equivalents of prednisolone: <i>adult and child over 20 kg</i>, 20 mg or more daily; <i>child under 20 kg</i>, 1 mg/kg or more daily] and chemotherapy);</li>
          <li>HIV infection (regardless of immune status).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Seasonal <xref format="dita" href="PHP8321.xml" type="drug">influenza vaccine</xref> is also recommended for all pregnant women, for all persons aged over 65 years, for residents of nursing or residential homes for the elderly and other long-stay facilities, and for carers of persons whose welfare may be at risk if the carer falls ill. Influenza immunisation should also be considered for household contacts of immunocompromised individuals.</p>
        <p>As part of winter planning, NHS employers should offer vaccination to healthcare workers who are directly involved in patient care. Employers of social care workers should consider similar action.</p>
        <p>Unless contra-indicated, the live <xref format="dita" href="PHP8321.xml" type="drug">influenza vaccine</xref>, <i>Fluenz Tetra</i><tm tmtype="reg" />, is preferred in children aged 2–18 years because it provides a higher level of protection than inactivated <xref format="dita" href="PHP8321.xml" type="drug">influenza vaccine</xref>i. From 1 September 2014, seasonal <xref format="dita" href="PHP8321.xml" type="drug">influenza vaccine</xref> will also be offered to all children aged 2–4 years (i.e. those born between 2 September 2009 and 1 September 2012).</p>
        <p>Information on pandemic influenza, avian influenza and swine influenza may be found at <xref format="html" href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/pandemicflu">www.dh.gov.uk/pandemicflu</xref> and at <xref format="html" href="http://www.gov.uk/phe">www.gov.uk/phe</xref>.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Japanese encephalitis vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8340.xml" type="drug">Japanese encephalitis vaccine</xref> is indicated for travellers to areas in Asia and the Far East where infection is endemic and for laboratory staff at risk of exposure to the virus. The primary immunisation course of 2 doses should be completed at least one week before potential exposure to Japanese encephalitis virus.</p>
        <p>Up-to-date information on the risk of Japanese encephalitis in specific countries can be obtained from the National Travel Health Network and Centre (<xref format="html" href="http://www.nathnac.org">www.nathnac.org</xref>).</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Measles, Mumps and Rubella vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <b>Measles vaccine</b> has been replaced by a combined live <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> (MMR vaccine).</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">Measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> aims to eliminate measles, mumps, and rubella (German measles) and congenital rubella syndrome. Every child should receive two doses of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> by entry to primary school, unless there is a valid contra-indication. <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">Measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> should be given irrespective of previous measles, mumps, or rubella infection or vaccination.</p>
        <p>The first dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> is given to children aged 12–13 months. A second dose is given before starting school at 3 years and 4 months–5 years of age (see Immunisation Schedule).</p>
        <p>Children presenting for pre-school booster who have not received the first dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> should be given a dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> followed 3 months later by a second dose.</p>
        <p>At school-leaving age or at entry into further education, <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> immunisation should be offered to individuals of both sexes who have not received 2 doses during childhood. In those who have received only a single dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> in childhood, a second dose is recommended to achieve full protection. If 2 doses of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> are required, the second dose should be given one month after the initial dose. The decision on whether to vaccinate adults should take into consideration their vaccination history, the likelihood of the individual remaining susceptible, and the future risk of exposure and disease.</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">Measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> should be used to protect against rubella in <i>seronegative women of child-bearing age</i> (see Immunisation Schedule); unimmunised healthcare workers who might put pregnant women and other vulnerable groups at risk of rubella or measles should be vaccinated. <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">Measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> may also be offered to previously <i>unimmunised and seronegative post-partum women</i> (see <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref>)—vaccination a few days after delivery is important because about 60% of congenital abnormalities from rubella infection occur in babies of women who have borne more than one child. Immigrants arriving after the age of school immunisation are particularly likely to require immunisation.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Contacts</p>
          <p>
            <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">Measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> may also be used in the control of outbreaks of measles and should be offered to susceptible children aged over 6 months who are contacts of a case, within 3 days of exposure to infection. Children immunised before 12 months of age should still receive two doses of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> at the recommended ages. If one dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> has already been given to a child, then the second dose may be brought forward to at least one month after the first, to ensure complete protection. If the child is under 18 months of age and the second dose is given within 3 months of the first, then the routine dose before starting school at 3 years and 4 months–5 years should still be given. Children aged under 9 months for whom avoidance of measles infection is particularly important (such as those with history of recent severe illness) can be given normal immunoglobulin after exposure to measles; routine <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> immunisation should then be given after at least 3 months at the appropriate age.</p>
          <p>
            <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">Measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> is <b>not suitable</b> for prophylaxis following exposure to mumps or rubella since the antibody response to the mumps and rubella components is too slow for effective prophylaxis.</p>
          <p>Children and adults with impaired immune response should not receive live vaccines (see advice on HIV). If they have been exposed to measles infection they should be given normal immunoglobulin.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Travel</p>
          <p>Unimmunised travellers, including children over 6 months, to areas where measles is endemic or epidemic should receive <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref>. Children immunised before 12 months of age should still receive two doses of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> at the recommended ages. If one dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8349.xml" type="drug">measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, live</xref> has already been given to a child, then the second dose should be brought forward to at least one month after the first, to ensure complete protection. If the child is under 18 months of age and the second dose is given within 3 months of the first, then the routine dose before starting school at 3 years and 4 months–5 years should still be given.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Meningococcal vaccine</p>
        <p>Almost all childhood meningococcal disease in the UK is caused by <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Neisseria meningitidis</i></i></ph> serogroups B and C. <b>Meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine</b> protects only against infection by serogroup C. The risk of meningococcal disease declines with age—immunisation is not generally recommended after the age of 25 years.</p>
        <p>Tetravalent meningococcal vaccines that cover serogroups A, C, W135, and Y are available. Although the duration of protection has not been established, the <b>meningococcal groups A, C, W135, and Y conjugate vaccine</b> is likely to provide longer-lasting protection than the unconjugated meningococcal polysaccharide vaccine. The antibody response to serogroup C in unconjugated meningococcal polysaccharide vaccines in young children may be suboptimal [not currently available in the UK].</p>
        <p>A <b>meningococcal group B vaccine</b>, <i>Bexsero</i><tm tmtype="reg" />, is licensed in the UK against infection caused by <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Neisseria meningitidis</i></i></ph> serogroup B. <i>Bexsero</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> contains 3 recombinant <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Neisseria meningitidis</i></i></ph> serogroup B proteins and the outer membrane vesicles from the NZ 98/254 strain, in order to achieve broad protection against <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Neisseria meningitidis</i></i></ph> serogroup B; the proteins are adsorbed onto an aluminium compound to stimulate an enhanced immune response.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Childhood immunisation</p>
          <p>
            <b>Meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine</b> provides long-term protection against infection by serogroup C of Neisseria meningitidis. Immunisation consists of 1 dose given at 3 months of age; 2 booster doses are recommended, the first is given at 12–13 months of age (combined with haemophilus influenzae type b vaccine), and the second at 13– 15 years of age (see Immunisation Schedule).</p>
          <p>Unimmunised children aged 4–12 months should be given 1 dose of meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine and then they should be vaccinated according to the Immunisation Schedule. Unimmunised children aged 1–10 years should be given 1 dose of meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine, followed by a booster dose at 13–15 years of age. Unimmunised individuals aged 10–25 years should be given 1 dose of meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine, but a booster dose is not required.</p>
          <p>From August 2014 there will be a catch-up programme for individuals aged under 25 years who are attending university for the first time and who did not receive a dose of meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine at 13–15 years of age.</p>
          <p>Patients under 25 years of age with confirmed serogroup C disease, who have previously been immunised with meningococcal group C vaccine, should be offered meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine before discharge from hospital.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Travel</p>
          <p>Individuals travelling to countries of risk should be immunised with meningococcal groups A, C, W135, and Y conjugate vaccine, even if they have previously received meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine. If an individual has recently received meningococcal group C conjugate vaccine, an interval of at least 4 weeks should be allowed before administration of the tetravalent (meningococcal groups A, C, W135, and Y) vaccine.</p>
          <p>Vaccination is particularly important for those living or working with local people or visiting an area of risk during outbreaks.</p>
          <p>Immunisation recommendations and requirements for visa entry for individual countries should be checked before travelling, particularly to countries in Sub-Saharan Africa, Asia, and the Indian sub-continent where epidemics of meningococcal outbreaks and infection are reported. Country-by-country information is available from the National Travel Health Network and Centre (www.nathnac.org).</p>
          <p>Proof of vaccination with the tetravalent meningococcal groups A with C and W135 and Y vaccine is required for those travelling to Saudi Arabia during the Hajj and Umrah pilgrimages (where outbreaks of the W135 strain have occurred).</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Contacts</p>
          <p>For advice on the immunisation of <i>laboratory workers and close contacts</i> of cases of meningococcal disease in the UK and on the role of the vaccine in the control of <i>local outbreaks</i>, consult Guidance for Public Health Management of Meningococcal Disease in the UK at <xref format="html" href="http://www.gov.uk/phe">www.gov.uk/phe</xref>. Also see for antibacterial prophylaxis for prevention of secondary cases of meningococcal meningitis.</p>
          <p>The need for immunisation of laboratory staff who work directly with <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Neisseria meningitidis</i></i></ph> should be considered.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Pertussis vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <b>Pertussis vaccine</b> is given as a combination preparation containing other vaccines. Acellular vaccines are derived from highly purified components of <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Bordetella pertussis</i></i></ph>. Primary immunisation against pertussis (whooping cough) requires 3 doses of an acellular pertussis-containing vaccine (see Immunisation schedule), given at intervals of 1 month from the age of 2 months.</p>
        <p>All children up to the age of 10 years should receive primary immunisation with diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component), poliomyelitis (inactivated) and haemophilus type b conjugate vaccine (adsorbed).</p>
        <p>A booster dose of an acellular pertussis-containing vaccine should ideally be given 3 years after the primary course, although, the interval can be reduced to 1 year if the primary course was delayed. Children aged 1–10 years who have not received a <i>pertussis-containing</i> vaccine as part of their primary immunisation should be offered 1 dose of a suitable pertussis-containing vaccine; after an interval of at least 1 year, a booster dose of a suitable pertussis-containing vaccine should be given. Immunisation against pertussis is not routinely recommended in individuals over 10 years of age.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Vaccination of pregnant women against pertussis</p>
          <p>In response to the pertussis outbreak, the UK health departments introduced a temporary programme (October 2012) to vaccinate pregnant women against pertussis, and this programme will continue until further notice. The aim of the programme is to boost the levels of pertussis–specific antibodies that are transferred through the placenta, from the mother to the fetus, so that the newborn is protected before routine immunisation begins at 2 months of age.</p>
          <p>Pregnant women should be offered a single dose of acellular pertussis-containing vaccine (as adsorbed diphtheria [low dose], tetanus, pertussis (acellular, component) and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine; <i>Boostrix-IPV</i><tm tmtype="reg" />) between 28 to 38 weeks of pregnancy; the optimal time for vaccination is between 28–32 weeks of pregnancy. Pregnant women should be offered a single dose of acellular pertussis-containing vaccine up to the onset of labour if they missed the opportunity for vaccination at 28–38 weeks of pregnancy. A single dose of acellular pertussis-containing vaccine may also be offered to new mothers, who have never previously been vaccinated against pertussis, until the child receives the first vaccination.</p>
          <p>While this programme is in place, women who become pregnant again should be offered vaccination during each pregnancy to maximise transplacental transfer of antibody.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Contacts</p>
          <p>Vaccination against pertussis should be considered for close contacts of cases with pertussis who have been offered antibacterial prophylaxis. Unimmunised or partially immunised contacts under 10 years of age should complete their vaccination against pertussis. A booster dose of an acellular pertussis-containing vaccine is recommended for contacts aged over 10 years who have not received a pertussis-containing vaccine in the last 5 years and who have not received adsorbed diphtheria [low dose], tetanus, and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine in the last month.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Side-effects</p>
          <p>Local reactions do not contra-indicate further doses.</p>
          <p>The vaccine should not be withheld from children with a history to a preceding dose of:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>fever, irrespective of severity;</li>
            <li>persistent crying or screaming for more than 3 hours;</li>
            <li>severe local reaction, irrespective of extent.</li>
          </ul>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Pneumococcal vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8373.xml" type="drug">Pneumococcal vaccine</xref> protects against infection with <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Streptococcus pneumoniae</i></i></ph> (pneumococcus); the vaccines contain polysaccharide from capsular pneumococci. <b>Pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine</b> contains purified polysaccharide from 23 capsular types of pneumococci, whereas <b>pneumococcal polysaccharide conjugate vaccine (adsorbed) </b>contains polysaccharide from either 10 capsular types (<i>Synflorix</i><tm tmtype="reg" />) or 13 capsular types (<i>Prevenar 13</i><tm tmtype="reg" />) and the polysaccharide is conjugated to protein.</p>
        <p>The 13-valent conjugate vaccine (<i>Prevenar 13</i><tm tmtype="reg" />) is used in the childhood immunisation schedule. The recommended schedule consists of 3 doses, the first at 2 months of age, the second at 4 months, and the third at 12–13 months (see Immunisation Schedule).</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8373.xml" type="drug">Pneumococcal vaccine</xref> is recommended for individuals at increased risk of pneumococcal infection as follows:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>age over 65 years;</li>
          <li>asplenia or splenic dysfunction (including homozygous sickle cell disease and coeliac disease which could lead to splenic dysfunction);</li>
          <li>chronic respiratory disease (includes asthma treated with continuous or frequent use of a systemic corticosteroid);</li>
          <li>chronic heart disease;</li>
          <li>chronic renal disease;</li>
          <li>chronic liver disease;</li>
          <li>diabetes mellitus requiring insulin or oral hypoglycaemic drugs;</li>
          <li>immune deficiency because of disease (e.g. HIV infection) or treatment (including prolonged systemic corticosteroid treatment for over 1 month at dose equivalents of prednisolone: <i>adult and child over 20 kg</i>, 20 mg or more daily; <i>child under 20 kg</i>, 1 mg/kg or more daily);</li>
          <li>presence of cochlear implant;</li>
          <li>conditions where leakage of cerebrospinal fluid may occur;</li>
          <li>child under 5 years with a history of invasive pneumococcal disease;</li>
          <li>at risk of occupational exposure to metal fume (e.g. welders).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Where possible, the vaccine should be given at least 2 weeks before splenectomy, cochlear implant surgery, chemotherapy, or radiotherapy; patients should be given advice about increased risk of pneumococcal infection. If it is not practical to vaccinate at least 2 weeks before splenectomy, chemotherapy, or radiotherapy, the vaccine should be given at least 2 weeks after the splenectomy or, where possible, at least 3 months after completion of chemotherapy or radiotherapy. Prophylactic antibacterial therapy against pneumococcal infection should not be stopped after immunisation. A patient card and information leaflet for patients with asplenia are available from the Department of Health or in Scotland from the Scottish Executive, Public Health Division 1 (Tel (0131) 244 2501).</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Choice of vaccine</p>
          <p>Children under 2 years at increased risk of pneumococcal infection (see list) should receive the 13-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide conjugate vaccine (adsorbed) at the recommended ages, followed by a single dose of the 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine after their second birthday. Children at increased risk of pneumococcal infection presenting late for vaccination should receive 2 doses (separated by at least 1 month) of the 13-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide conjugate vaccine (adsorbed) before the age of 12 months, and a third dose at 12–13 months. Children over 12 months and under 5 years (who have not been vaccinated or not completed the primary course) should receive a single dose of the 13-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide conjugate vaccine (adsorbed) (2 doses separated by an interval of 2 months in the immunocompromised or those with asplenia or splenic dysfunction). All children under 5 years at increased risk of pneumococcal infection should receive a single dose of the 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine after their second birthday and at least 2 months after the final dose of the 13-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide conjugate vaccine (adsorbed).</p>
          <p>Children over 5 years and adults who are at increased risk of pneumococcal disease should receive a single dose of the 23-valent unconjugated pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Revaccination</p>
          <p>In individuals with higher concentrations of antibodies to pneumococcal polysaccharides, revaccination with the 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine more commonly produces adverse reactions. Revaccination is therefore not recommended, except every 5 years in individuals in whom the antibody concentration is likely to decline rapidly (e.g. asplenia, splenic dysfunction and nephrotic syndrome). If there is doubt, the need for revaccination should be discussed with a haematologist, immunologist, or microbiologist.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Poliomyelitis vaccine</p>
        <p>Two types of poliomyelitis vaccines (containing strains of poliovirus types 1, 2, and 3) are available, inactivated poliomyelitis vaccine (for injection) and live (oral) poliomyelitis vaccine. <b>Inactivated</b> poliomyelitis vaccines, only available in combined preparation, is recommended for routine immunisation.</p>
        <p>A course of primary immunisation consists of 3 doses of a combined preparation containing inactivated poliomyelitis vaccines, starting at 2 months of age with intervals of 1 month between doses (see Immunisation schedule). A course of 3 doses should also be given to all unimmunised adults; no adult should remain unimmunised against poliomyelitis.</p>
        <p>Two booster doses of a preparation containing inactivated poliomyelitis vaccines are recommended, the first before school entry and the second before leaving school (see Immunisation schedule). Further booster doses are only necessary for adults at special risk, such as travellers to endemic areas, or laboratory staff likely to be exposed to the viruses, or healthcare workers in possible contact with cases; booster doses should be given to such individuals every 10 years.</p>
        <p>
          <b>Live (oral) poliomyelitis vaccine</b> is no longer available for routine use; its use may be considered during large outbreaks, but advice should be sought from Public Health England. The live (oral) vaccine poses a very rare risk of vaccine-associated paralytic polio because the attenuated strain of the virus can revert to a virulent form. For this reason the live (oral) vaccine must <b>not</b> be used for immunosuppressed individuals or their household contacts. The use of inactivated poliomyelitis vaccines removes the risk of vaccine-associated paralytic polio altogether. </p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Travel</p>
          <p>Unimmunised travellers to areas with a high incidence of poliomyelitis should receive a full 3-dose course of a preparation containing inactivated poliomyelitis vaccines. Those who have not been vaccinated in the last 10 years should receive a booster dose of <b>adsorbed diphtheria [low dose], tetanus and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b>. Information about countries with a high incidence of poliomyelitis can be obtained from www.travax.nhs.uk or from the National Travel Health Network and Centre (<xref format="html" href="http://www.nathnac.org">www.nathnac.org</xref>).</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Rabies vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8391.xml" type="drug">Rabies vaccine</xref> contains inactivated rabies virus cultivated in either human diploid cells or purified chick embryo cells; vaccines are used for pre- and post-exposure prophylaxis.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Pre-exposure prophylaxis</p>
          <p>Immunisation should be offered to those at high risk of exposure to rabies— laboratory staff who handle the rabies virus, those working in quarantine stations, animal handlers, veterinary surgeons and field workers who are likely to be bitten by infected wild animals, certain port officials, and bat handlers. Transmission of rabies by humans has not been recorded but it is advised that those caring for patients with the disease should be vaccinated.</p>
          <p>Immunisation against rabies is also recommended where there is limited access to prompt medical care for those living in areas where rabies is enzootic, for those travelling to such areas for longer than 1 month, and for those on shorter visits who may be exposed to unusual risk.</p>
          <p>Immunisation against rabies is indicated during pregnancy if there is substantial risk of exposure to rabies and rapid access to post-exposure prophylaxis is likely to be limited.</p>
          <p>Up-to-date country-by-country information on the incidence of rabies can be obtained from the National Travel Health Network and Centre (<xref format="html" href="http://www.nathnac.org">www.nathnac.org</xref>) and, in Scotland, from Health Protection Scotland (<xref format="html" href="http://www.hps.scot.nhs.uk">www.hps.scot.nhs.uk</xref>).</p>
          <p>Immunisation against rabies requires 3 doses of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8391.xml" type="drug">rabies vaccine</xref>, with further booster doses for those who remain at frequent risk. To ensure continued protection in persons at high risk (e.g. laboratory workers), the concentration of antirabies antibodies in plasma is used to determine the intervals between doses.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Post-exposure management</p>
          <p>Following potential exposure to rabies, the wound or site of exposure (e.g. mucous membrane) should be cleansed under running water and washed for several minutes with soapy water as soon as possible after exposure. Disinfectant and a simple dressing can be applied, but suturing should be delayed because it may increase the risk of introducing rabies virus into the nerves.</p>
          <p>Post-exposure prophylaxis against rabies depends on the level of risk in the country, the nature of exposure, and the individual’s immunity. In each case, expert risk assessment and advice on appropriate management should be obtained from the local Public Health England Centre or Public Health England’s Virus Reference Department, Colindale (tel. (020) 8200 4400) or the PHE Colindale Duty Doctor (tel. (020) 8200 6868), in Wales from the Public Health Wales local Health Protection Team or Public Health Wales Virus Reference Laboratory (tel. (029) 2074 7747), in Scotland from the local on-call infectious diseases consultant, and in Northern Ireland from the Public Health Agency Duty Room (tel (028) 9055 3997/ (028) 9063 2662) or the Regional Virology Service (tel. (028) 9024 0503).</p>
          <p>There are no specific contra-indications to the use of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8391.xml" type="drug">rabies vaccine</xref> for post-exposure prophylaxis and its use should be considered whenever a patient has been attacked by an animal in a country where rabies is enzootic, even if there is no direct evidence of rabies in the attacking animal. Because of the potential consequences of untreated rabies exposure and because rabies vaccination has not been associated with fetal abnormalities, pregnancy is not considered a contraindication to post-exposure prophylaxis.</p>
          <p>For post-exposure prophylaxis of <i>fully immunised</i> individuals (who have previously received pre-exposure or post-exposure prophylaxis with cell-derived rabies vaccine), 2 doses of cell-derived vaccine are likely to be sufficient; the first dose is given on day 0 and the second dose is given between day 3–7. <xref format="dita" href="PHP8470.xml" type="drug">Rabies immunoglobulin</xref> is not necessary in such cases.</p>
          <p>Post-exposure treatment for<i>unimmunised individuals</i> (or those whose prophylaxis is possibly incomplete) comprises 5 doses of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8391.xml" type="drug">rabies vaccine</xref> given over 1 month (on days 0, 3, 7, 14, and the fifth dose is given between day 28–30); also, depending on the level of risk (determined by factors such as the nature of the bite and the country where it was sustained), <xref format="dita" href="PHP8470.xml" type="drug">rabies immunoglobulin</xref> is given to unimmunised individuals on day 0 or within 7 days of starting the course of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8391.xml" type="drug">rabies vaccine</xref>. The immunisation course can be discontinued if it is proved that the individual was not at risk.</p>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Rotavirus vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8396.xml" type="drug">Rotavirus vaccine</xref> is a live, oral vaccine that protects young children against gastro-enteritis caused by rotavirus infection. The recommended schedule consists of 2 doses, the first at 2 months of age, and the second at 3 months of age (see Immunisation schedule). The first dose of <xref format="dita" href="PHP8396.xml" type="drug">rotavirus vaccine</xref> must be given between 6–15 weeks of age and the second dose should be given after an interval of at least 4 weeks; the vaccine should not be started in children 15 weeks of age or older. Ideally, the full course should be completed before 16 weeks of age to provide protection before the main burden of disease, and to avoid a temporal association between vaccination and intussusception; the course must be completed before 24 weeks of age.</p>
        <p>The <xref format="dita" href="PHP8396.xml" type="drug">rotavirus vaccine</xref> virus is excreted in the stool and may be transmitted to close contacts; however, vaccination of those with <i>immunosuppressed</i> close contacts may protect the contacts from wild-type rotavirus disease and outweigh any risk from transmission of vaccine virus. Carers of a recently vaccinated baby should be advised of the need to wash their hands after changing the baby’s nappies.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Smallpox vaccine</p>
        <p>Limited supplies of <b>smallpox vaccine</b> are held at the Specialist and Reference Microbiology Division, Public Health England Colindale (Tel. (020) 8200 4400) for the exclusive use of workers in laboratories where pox viruses (such as vaccinia) are handled.</p>
        <p>If a wider use of the vaccine is being considered, <i>Guidelines for smallpox response and management in the post-eradication era</i> should be consulted at <xref format="html" href="http://www.gov.uk/phe">www.gov.uk/phe</xref>.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Tetanus vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <b>Tetanus vaccine</b> contains a cell-free purified toxin of <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Clostridium tetani</i></i></ph> adsorbed on aluminium hydroxide or aluminium phosphate to improve antigenicity.</p>
        <p>Primary immunisation for children under 10 years consists of 3 doses of a combined preparation containing adsorbed tetanus vaccine, with an interval of 1 month between doses. Following routine childhood vaccination, 2 booster doses of a preparation containing adsorbed tetanus vaccine are recommended, the first before school entry and the second before leaving school (see Immunisation schedule).</p>
        <p>The recommended schedule of tetanus vaccination not only gives protection against tetanus in childhood but also gives the basic immunity for subsequent booster doses. In most circumstances, a total of 5 doses of tetanus vaccine is considered sufficient for long term protection.</p>
        <p>For primary immunisation of adults and children over 10 years previously unimmunised against tetanus, 3 doses of <b>adsorbed diphtheria [low dose], tetanus and poliomyelitis (inactivated) vaccine</b> are given with an interval of 1 month between doses (see Diphtheria-containing Vaccines).</p>
        <p>When an individual presents for a booster dose but has been vaccinated following a tetanus-prone wound, the vaccine preparation administered at the time of injury should be determined. If this is not possible, the booster should still be given to ensure adequate protection against all antigens in the booster vaccine.</p>
        <p>Very rarely, tetanus has developed after abdominal surgery; patients awaiting elective surgery should be asked about tetanus immunisation and immunised if necessary.</p>
        <p>Parenteral drug abuse is also associated with tetanus; those abusing drugs by injection should be vaccinated if unimmunised—booster doses should be given if there is any doubt about their immunisation status.</p>
        <p>All laboratory staff should be offered a primary course if unimmunised.</p>
        <sectiondiv>
          <p outputclass="title">Wounds</p>
          <p>Wounds are considered to be tetanus-prone if they are sustained more than 6 hours before surgical treatment or at any interval after injury and are puncture-type (particularly if contaminated with soil or manure) <i>or</i> show much devitalised tissue <i>or</i> are septic <i>or</i> are compound fractures <i>or</i> contain foreign bodies. All wounds should receive thorough cleansing.</p>
          <ul>
            <li>For <i>clean wounds</i>: fully immunised individuals (those who have received a total of 5 doses of a tetanus-containing vaccine at appropriate intervals) and those whose primary immunisation is complete (with boosters up to date), do not require tetanus vaccine; individuals whose primary immunisation is incomplete or whose boosters are not up to date require a reinforcing dose of a tetanus-containing vaccine (followed by further doses as required to complete the schedule); non-immunised individuals (or those whose immunisation status is not known or who have been fully immunised but are now immunocompromised) should be given a dose of the appropriate tetanus-containing vaccine immediately (followed by completion of the full course of the vaccine if records confirm the need)</li>
            <li>For <i>tetanus-prone wounds</i>: management is as for clean wounds with the addition of a dose of tetanus immunoglobulin given at a different site; in fully immunised individuals and those whose primary immunisation is complete (with boosters up to date) the immunoglobulin is needed only if the risk of infection is especially high (e.g. contamination with manure). Antibacterial prophylaxis (with benzylpenicillin, co-amoxiclav, or metronidazole) may also be required for tetanus-prone wounds.</li>
          </ul>
        </sectiondiv>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Tick-borne encephalitis vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8407.xml" type="drug">Tick-borne encephalitis vaccine, inactivated</xref> contains inactivated tick-borne encephalitis virus cultivated in chick embryo cells. It is recommended for immunisation of those working in, or visiting, high-risk areas (see International Travel). Those working, walking or camping in warm forested areas of Central and Eastern Europe, Scandinavia, Northern and Eastern China, and some parts of Japan, particularly from April to November when ticks are most prevalent, are at greatest risk of tick-borne encephalitis. For full protection, 3 doses of the vaccine are required; booster doses are required every 3–5 years for those still at risk. Ideally, immunisation should be completed at least one month before travel.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Typhoid vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8411.xml" type="drug">Typhoid vaccine</xref> is available as Vi capsular polysaccharide (from <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Salmonella typhi</i></i></ph>) vaccine for injection and as live attenuated <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Salmonella typhi</i></i></ph> for oral use.</p>
        <p>Typhoid immunisation is advised for:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>travellers to areas where typhoid is endemic, especially if staying with or visiting local people;</li>
          <li>travellers to endemic areas where frequent or prolonged exposure to poor sanitation and poor food hygiene is likely</li>
          <li>laboratory personnel who, in the course of their work, may be exposed to <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Salmonella typhi</i></i></ph>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Typhoid vaccination is not a substitute for scrupulous personal hygiene.</p>
        <p>Capsular <b>polysaccharide</b><xref format="dita" href="PHP8411.xml" type="drug">typhoid vaccine</xref> is usually given by <i>intramuscular injection</i>. Children under 2 years may respond suboptimally to the vaccine, but children aged between 1–2 years should be immunised if the risk of typhoid fever is considered high (immunisation is not recommended for infants under 12 months). Revaccination is needed every 3 years on continued exposure.</p>
        <p>
          <b>Oral</b>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8411.xml" type="drug">typhoid vaccine</xref> is a <b>live attenuated </b>vaccine contained in an enteric-coated capsule. One capsule taken on alternate days for a total of 3 doses, provides protection 7–10 days after the last dose. Protection may persist for up to 3 years in those constantly (or repeatedly) exposed to <ph outputclass="organism"><i><i>Salmonella typhi</i></i></ph>, but those who only occasionally travel to endemic areas require further courses at intervals of 1 year.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Varicella-zoster vaccine</p>
        <p>The live <xref format="dita" href="PHP8420.xml" type="drug">varicella-zoster vaccine</xref>, <i>Varilrix</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> and <i>Varivax</i><tm tmtype="reg" />, are licensed for immunisation against varicella (chickenpox) in seronegative individuals. They are not recommended for routine use in children, but can be given to seronegative healthy children over 1 year who come into close contact with individuals at high risk of severe varicella infections. The Department of Health recommends these vaccines for seronegative healthcare workers who come into direct contact with patients. Those with a history of chickenpox or shingles can be considered immune, but healthcare workers with a negative or uncertain history should be tested.</p>
        <p>Rarely, the <xref format="dita" href="PHP8420.xml" type="drug">varicella-zoster vaccine</xref> virus has been transmitted from the vaccinated individual to close contacts. Therefore, contact with the following should be avoided if a vaccine-related cutaneous rash develops within 4–6 weeks of the first or second dose:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>varicella-susceptible pregnant women;</li>
          <li>individuals at high risk of severe varicella, including those with immunodeficiency or those receiving immunosuppressive therapy;</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Healthcare workers who develop a generalised papular or vesicular rash on vaccination should avoid contact with patients until the lesions have crusted. Those who develop a localised rash after vaccination should cover the lesions and be allowed to continue working unless in contact with patients at high risk of severe varicella.</p>
        <p>The high potency, live <xref format="dita" href="PHP8420.xml" type="drug">varicella-zoster vaccine</xref>, <i>Zostavax</i><tm tmtype="reg" />, is recommended for the prevention of <i>herpes zoster</i> (shingles) in adults who are, or were, 70 years of age on 1 September 2014. The 2014-15, catch-up programme with <i>Zostavax</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> will be offered to all who are, or were, 78 or 79 years of age on 1 September 2014. A single dose of <i>Zostavax</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> is likely to give protection for at least 7 years, but the need for, or timing of, a booster dose has not been established. Although <i>Zostavax</i><tm tmtype="reg" /> is not recommended for the treatment of shingles or post-herpetic neuralgia, it can be given to those with a previous history of shingles; ideally the vaccine should be delayed until systemic antiviral therapy has been completed.</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8476.xml" type="drug">Varicella-zoster immunoglobulin</xref> is used to protect susceptible individuals at increased risk of varicella infection.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p outputclass="title">Yellow fever vaccine</p>
        <p>
          <xref format="dita" href="PHP8427.xml" type="drug">Yellow fever vaccine, live</xref> is indicated for those travelling or living in areas where infection is endemic and for laboratory staff who handle the virus or who handle clinical material from suspected cases. Infants under 6 months of age should not be vaccinated because there is a small risk of encephalitis; infants aged 6–9 months should be vaccinated only if the risk of yellow fever is high and unavoidable (seek expert advice). The immunity which probably lasts for life is officially accepted for 10 years starting from 10 days after primary immunisation and for a further 10 years immediately after revaccination.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
